Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ז. yod zayin.
We take up with a new משנה. mishna. And as maybe you've
been noting, the משניות mishnayot and the discussion are starting to get
into, I think, more like conceptual issues, moving away from some of
the technical language issues. So, you know, we had the משנה mishna
about, I mean it moved from a language distinction between a שבועה
shevua and a נדר neder to say this is ways in which
a שבועה shevua is more strict than a נדר, neder, and then
it pointed out about the ways נדרים nedarim are more strict or
whatever have a wider effect that a נדר neder can prevent the
performance of a מצוה mitzvah by making the object forbidden, and thereby
sort of indirectly prevent somebody to perform a מצוה mitzvah where a
שבועה shevua would be directly going against the person's obligation and would
not take effect. And then that also led us to an interesting
discussion about whether a person can take a נדר neder to make
something not only forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, in benefit, because מצוות mitzvot
are not considered to be a הלכתי halakhic form of benefit, but
actually make things forbidden in terms of performing certain actions with them.
So that was also very important in terms of that issue about
what the nature of something being forbidden by a נדר neder can
be, if it has to only limit itself to the world of
eating and benefit or can it even apply to other aspects as
well. We now turn to our משנה mishna on י"ז, yod zayin,
which also deals with the difference between נדר neder and שבועה, shevua,
and also to some degree related to this issue of object versus
person, although maybe a little less directly. Let's take a look. יש
נדר בתוך נדר ואין שבועה בתוך שבועה. Yesh neder betoch neder ve'ein
shevua betoch shevua. A person can make a נדר neder literally inside
of a נדר, neder, or I, we might say, on top of
another נדר, neder, but not a שבועה, shevua, again I'll use our
idiom, on top of another שבועה. shevua. כיצד? Keitzad? אמר הרי אני
נזיר. Amar harei ani nazir.
So it's interesting that the immediate example it gives of a נדר
neder is a נזיר. nazir. Okay, I mean the Torah says איש
כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר, ish ki yafli lindor neder nazir, so
it says the word נדר neder twice even by a נזיר. nazir.
It is a type of a נדר, neder, especially to the degree
that you understand again that a נדר neder is about using your
speech act to change the status of something. So here, instead of
changing the status of an object, you're changing the status of you
as a person. You are imparting upon yourself the status of being
a נזיר. nazir. Again, that's another example of a status that is
not about forbidden הנאה hana'ah that has other implications. Okay, so that
is a type of a נדר, neder, and actually that is the
only נדר neder that fits into this case in the משנה, mishna,
a נדר neder on top of a נדר. neder. We'll talk why
in a minute. Okay. יש נדר בתוך נדר ואין שבועה בתוך שבועה.
Yesh neder betoch neder ve'ein shevua betoch shevua. כיצד? Keitzad? אמר הרי
אני נזיר אם אוכל הרי אני נזיר אם אוכל. Amar harei ani
nazir im ochal, harei ani nazir im ochal. ואכל. Ve'achal. I will
be a נזיר nazir if I eat this piece of bread, I
will be a נזיר nazir if I eat this piece of bread.
And he ate the piece of bread. חייב על כל אחת ואחת.
Chayav al kol achat ve'achat. He's obligated for each one. Now, a
simple read of that might be you're a double נזיר, nazir, and
now if at the end of thirty days you bring two sets
of קרבנות korbanot or if you go ahead and you willingly eat
grapes you get two sets of lashes. That is not what the
גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara actually says that what it means
is that after your first נזירות nezirut is over, your second נזירות
nezirut kicks in. Okay, so right, so you'll be a total of
sixty days, but it'll be two sets of thirty, because at the
end of thirty you'll bring קרבנות, korbanot, and then you stop one,
and then you complete and do all the קרבנות, korbanot, and then
you do the other. Okay, so what it actually means is that
the other נזירות nezirut is sort of like hovering, waiting to take
effect as soon as the first status gets removed. Because the basic
actual principle is, and in this way it's important, that a שבועה
shevua and a נדר neder is the same, it really cannot take
effect one on top of the other. But the point by נזיר
nazir is that, okay, it hasn't taken effect but it's sitting there
and it's hovering. Now שבועה שלא אוכל שבועה שלא אוכל, shevua shelo
ochal, shevua shelo ochal, so if he says a שבועה shevua I
won't eat, a שבועה shevua I won't eat, ואכל, ve'achal, and then
they ate, אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino chayav ela achat, they've only
transgressed their שבועה shevua once. Why? Because this is the same principle
we said by a משנה, mishna, it's מושבע ועומד מהר סיני. mushba
ve'omed mehar Sinai. Or not מהר סיני, mehar Sinai, מושבע ועומד, mushba
ve'omed, a person took a שבועה, shevua, they're already obligated, so there's
a principle that a שבועה shevua to obligate you to do something,
right, does not take effect if you are already obligated. Now I
do want to make a point about this, because this is not
as obvious as it might seem, because it's first of all it's
not the same as a שבועה shevua to countermand your obligation, a
שבועה shevua that I won't sit in a סוכה. sukkah. Okay, you
could say that's a שבועת שוא, shevuat shav, right, but that you've
already done something wrong by taking an oath to countermand your obligation,
but it does not now remain to become an obligation upon you.
A שבועה shevua to do something you're already obligated in is less
clear why it wouldn't take effect, especially depends how you conceptualize the
idea of שבועה, shevua, and this is a very important point, right?
Because נדר neder we've already abstracted, נדר neder we've already said like
I am changing the status of this object to be a forbidden
object. But how do we understand it when I say a שבועה
shevua I'm going to go to the store today? Okay, have I
created this abstract thing called an obligation to go to the store?
So the same way the Torah can obligate me to do something,
now my שבועה shevua is obligating me to do something, right? And
is... I have taken God's name and a lie essentially, okay, as
so I have violated that that statement. So it's less that I
have this obligation to go to the store and more that by
not going to the store, it will turn out that I have
violated my שבועה, Shvua, you know, I've taken God's name wrongly. If
that's the way you think about it, let's talk about the idea
of a שבועה Shvua to do something I'm already obligated in. A
שבועה Shvua to put on תפילין, Tefillin, a שבועה Shvua to sit
in a סוכה, Sukkah, a שבועה Shvua that I said I won't
eat and then I'll take another שבועה Shvua on top of that
that I won't eat. So why is it that you would say
one שבועה Shvua doesn't take effect on top of the other? If
I go ahead and I don't put on תפילין, Tefillin, I've violated
my biblical מצוה, Mitzvah, and it turns out that I've sworn falsely.
I took an oath in God's name that I would do something,
right?
So why is that still not a problem? I didn't do what
I said I was going to do, even though I was already
obligated to do it. It really the idea of אין שבועה חלה
על שבועה Ein Shvua Chala al Shvua really seems to create an
abstract idea that my שבועה Shvua creates an obligation, right? Because I
took an oath that I would put on תפילין, Tefillin, okay, that
creates an obligation to put on תפילין. Tefillin. And the answer is,
well, you can't obligate yourself to put on תפילין Tefillin because you're
already pre-obligated. It doesn't mean anything to obligate yourself to put on
תפילין. Tefillin. Okay, so do you understand the point I'm making, meaning
if we think about it like a נדר, Neder, we understand actually
the logic is אין נדר חל על נדר. Ein Neder Chal al
Neder. We'll get to נזיר Nazir in a minute, but if this
thing is already forbidden, you can't make it forbidden on top of
being forbidden. If I'm already obligated to do something, you can't I
can't make myself obligated on top of being obligated. I'm already obligated,
what does it mean to say I'm obligated twice? Okay, so that's
the idea of, you know, I'm already מושבע ועומד Mushba ve'omed or
אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. Ein Shvua Chala al Shvua. But I
just want to point out that that's a חידוש, Chidush, because I
might have said when I say a שבועה Shvua that I'm going
to put on תפילין, Tefillin, I'm not creating an obligation. Okay, but
what it means is is that I have an obligation but if
I don't, then I've sworn falsely, because I, you know... so somehow
we move away from that act of taking an oath in the
name of God and what's it like a true oath or not
a true oath and we talk about how that generates an obligation.
And since that generates an obligation, you can't create an obligation on
something you're already obligated on. So if I already took a שבועה
Shvua that I wouldn't eat this loaf of bread and now I'm
obligated not to eat it, I can't obligate myself on top of
that not to eat it because I'm already obligated not to eat
it. But again, that is focusing on the שבועה Shvua as generating
an obligation, not as the שבועה Shvua as, you know, as swearing
falsely. Okay, just contrast it to a שבועה Shvua in the past.
A שבועה Shvua about something in the past is clearly about have
I sworn falsely or sworn truly. But a שבועה Shvua in this
future seems to be about generating an obligation. Wait just one second,
now logically, if that's true about a שבועה, Shvua, you would say
almost קל וחומר Kal ve-chomer about a נדר. Neder. If something is
already forbidden, I can't make it forbidden on top of being forbidden.
We actually have a phrase for that in הלכה. Halacha. You know
what the phrase for that in הלכה Halacha is called? Thank you.
אין איסור חל על איסור. Ein Issur Chal al Issur. One prohibition
cannot take effect on top of another one, and that has nothing
to do even with my speech acts. If something is already, I
don't know, you know, בשר בחלב, Basar Bechalav, a נבילה Neveilah can
it also become בשר בחלב? Basar Bechalav? You know, maybe not, because
it already has a forbidden status, so you maybe you can't have
multiple statuses, which is a little funny, because in some reason like
why not? Why can't it be forbidden in multiple ways? But we
already have that concept by an object, that it can't be forbidden
on top of being forbidden. So why can a נדר Neder take
effect on top of another נדר? Neder? And the actual answer is
it can't, okay, which is why a normal נדר, Neder, if I
said קונם כיכר זה עלי, קונם כיכר זה עלי, Konam kikar ze
alai, konam kikar ze alai, the second one would mean nothing. And
even when I say הריני נזיר, הריני נזיר, Hareini Nazir, hareini Nazir,
the second one does not immediately mean anything, because you can't have
one status taking effect on top of the other. The only difference
is is that נזיר Nazir is something that will terminate. And because
it will terminate, when it does terminate, the other one, it wasn't
like it disappeared, it was like an obligation waiting to take effect,
and when that goes away, the other one kicks in. And you
can have something like that like אין איסור חל על איסור Ein
Issur Chal al Issur as well. Okay, so if one איסור Issur
goes away, the other one might then kick in exactly at the...
it's like hovering, okay. So then the question then becomes, so why
can't you have a similar idea of hovering, I don't know, by
a שבועה Shvua or by a normal נדר? Neder? שבועה Shvua I
won't eat this loaf of bread today, right? שבועה Shvua I won't
eat this loaf of bread today. So why don't you say, well,
the second one is hovering, and when the day is over, the
second one kicks in? Well, then it's no longer today. So why
don't you say שבועה Shvua I won't eat this loaf of bread
today, שבועה Shvua I won't eat this loaf of bread? Right, so
then maybe it does kick in at that time. Anyway, the point
is is that all of a sudden you start realizing that number
one, it's not so clear why this is a problem by שבועה,
Shvua, because שבועה Shvua if you focus on the swearing falsely or
swearing truly, it's less an issue of obligation on top of obligation.
And it's not so clear why it it does work by a
נדר, neder, or classic נדר neder actually, it doesn't work, אין איסור
חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. So in a way,
the real point about all of this is number one, by a
שבועה shavuah we focus on creating an obligation and we say one
obligation does not take place on top of another. נדר neder we
focus on creating a status and we say one status does not
take place on top of another. And what we are really left
with is a concept of a נזיר, nazir, because the concept of
a נזיר nazir is intrinsically a sort of a, you know, something
that is a unit. It's not like indefinite. By very nature, it's
a unit that's performed and is over with and has a terminal
point. When a person tries to accept two נזירות, neziruses, we see
the first one as being sort of a temporary status, you know,
or a time-bound type of a thing, and the second one waiting
to kick in. So really it's a חידוש chiddush by נזירות nezirus
that the idea that it's hovering and it's waiting to kick in.
Now there were a few questions. Yes, David.
Can you make a distinction between a מצוה mitzvah and a commitment
to do the מצוה, mitzvah, like, you know, you
are, you are obligated. Right.
Well, yeah, that's like the idea of the גמרא Gemara before about
מניין שנשבעין לקיים את המצוה, minayin shenishba'in lekayem es hamitzvah, that sometimes
we need to push ourselves to do things we're already obligated in.
Right. And, you know, remember like נשבעתי ואקיימה nishbati va'akayema and the
גמרא Gemara before, right? Remember that גמרא Gemara way back on what
it was, דף ח daf ches or something? And that was the
famous גמרא Gemara because it
read מניין שנשבעין לקיים את המצוה, שנאמר נשבעתי ואקיימה לשמור משפטי צדקך.
minayin shenishba'in lekayem es hamitzvah, shene'emar nishbati va'akayema lishmor mishpetei tzidkecha. And
the גמרא Gemara said, והלא מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא, vehalo mushba
ve'omed mehar Sinai hu, right?
What do you mean? You can't obligate yourself, you're already obligated. So
it says דשרי ליה לאיניש לזרוזי נפשיה. desharei lei le'inish lezarzuzei nafshei.
You can do it just to sort of encourage yourself, push yourself.
Okay, but it might not really be binding, okay, in a technical
sense. Okay. That was ח, ches, that was ח עמוד א. ches
amud aleph. Right. So that actually technically was an issue, but לזרוזי
נפשיה lezarzuzei nafshei sort of means okay, like מדרבנן, miderabbanan, or you
know, it's some type of a, right, but yes, exactly that. Uh-huh.
Can go... okay. All right. So that is the idea. So again,
we have the idea that by a שבועה shavuah you're already obligated
or forbidden, it can't take effect on top of it. By נדר
neder we should say the same and it's really נזיר nazir that
winds
up to be different. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
By the way, I should point out that a number of ראשונים,
Rishonim, the רן Ran has a גירסא girsa in the גמרא, Gemara,
probably it was a later גירסא, girsa, that the גמרא Gemara actually
says... that's not in our גמרא, Gemara, but I'll just tell you
what it says. One part of what it said was why did
you have to say I'll be a נזיר nazir if I eat,
a נזיר nazir if I eat? Why didn't you just say I'm
a נזיר, nazir, I'm a נזיר, nazir, right? And that'll have the
same idea. Why did you have to make it conditional on if
I eat? So the... so the גמרא Gemara answered, and if it's
not in your גמרא, Gemara, the ראשונים Rishonim answer, and they basically
say, yeah, but because by שבועה shavuah we're going to take... about
taking a שבועה shavuah that you won't eat, when we want to
speak about נזיר, nazir, we wanted also bring in the idea of
eating or not eating or whatever, but it's really immaterial. It could
have just said I'm a נזיר, nazir, I'm a נזיר, nazir, there
the second one will take effect when the first one is finished
as opposed to I won't eat, I won't eat. The other point
to be made is I thought a fascinating one, which is if
somebody said הריני נזיר hareini nazir if I eat from this loaf
of bread, okay, and they ate a כזית kezayis and then they
ate another כזית kezayis and then they ate another כזית, kezayis, are
they now a נזיר nazir three times? Right? And each one is
waiting to take effect when the other one finishes? Because it said
if I eat I'll be a נזיר. nazir. So I ate, I'm
a נזיר. nazir. Or do we say no, no, anything else that
you only meant it once? So actually some have the גירסא girsa
in the... in the גמרא, Gemara,
totally not in our גמרא, Gemara, that actually says that if a
person was warned between the two, because this is a normal question
in general, right, about when do we say that it's separate acts
and one act. If I have a piece of חזיר chazir in
front of me and Charlie says, don't eat it, you'll get lashes.
This of course reminds me of that... of the joke. You know
the joke? The guy... the guy's in France and he's never had
a chance, like, you know, to have like... you know... I mean
whatever, he's... there's nobody else around, you know, he's finally alone, he's
always wanted to have like roast pig. So he goes to the
restaurant and he orders like this roast pig and they bring it
out to him, you know, and it's... you know... the whole thing
with all of the trimmings and the apple in the mouth and
they bring out the whole platter. And then as just as he's
about to dig in, like somebody's walking by and looks into the
window and then sees him and says, Chaim, what are you doing?
So he says, Oh my god, you order an apple, look how
they פּאַטשקע patchke it up!
Oh, yeah,
a rabbi once saw Chaim is eating and somebody says what have
you done? He said listen, I'm under strictly biblical supervision.
Ah, no, mine is a funnier
punchline.
Anyway, okay, so anyway, so there... so there Chaim is and he's
about to eat from the pig and Charlie says, don't eat, you'll
get lashes. And he says no, I don't care, I'm going to
eat from it. He doesn't give the punchline. And he eats and
he eats and he eats and he eats and he eats. How
many lashes does he get? Yes, only one, because that's one act
of ongoing eating, which is just a lot that he ate. Let's
say however he eats a כזית kezayis and then Charlie says, I
told you, don't eat from it, you'll get lashes. And he says,
I don't care, I'm going to eat from it, and he eats
another כזית. kezayis. And then again and again, then for each separate
thing he gets another set of lashes, because each one is considered
a separate act. Okay, so that's when it comes to getting lashes.
So some have the גירסא girsa in this גמרא Gemara that the
same would be true about defining it as a separate act for
this נדר neder or for this... If I said I'll be a
נזיר nazir if I eat from this loaf of bread and I
eat from it, poof, I'm a נזיר. nazir. Then Charlie said, טוב,
tov, what are you doing? You don't want to become a נזיר,
nazir, better not eat some of it anymore or you'll be a
נזיר nazir again. And I said, I don't care, and I eat
from it again. So some way in which he that act gets
separate because he says, you know, if you continue eating from it
you're going to, and I go ahead and I do it anyway.
So it's not about being punished, but it's about separating the acts.
And somehow that נדר neder is seen as not just to be
kicked in once, but if I say if I eat then every
time I eat would somehow trigger. That would be another חידוש chiddush
of the משנה. Mishna. Not just that you have another נזירות neziros
waiting to take effect, but that one נדר neder for a נזיר
nazir can generate multiple נזירות neziros if you make it conditional. That
would really be an interesting חידוש. chiddush. Okay. That's not explicit in
our משנה Mishna and certainly not in our גמרא, Gemara, but some
had that discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at
our גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, לא שנו
אלא דאמר הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר למחר. Lo shanu ela de’amar
hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir lemakhar. When is it that the second
נזירות neziros can take effect? That it's not completely redundant, it's seen
as distinct from the first one? If you said I'm a נזיר
nazir today and then you said I'll also be a נזיר nazir
beginning tomorrow.
Okay. דמיגו דקא מתוסף יומא יתירא, Demigo deka mitosef yoma yetira, since
by saying you'll be a נזיר nazir tomorrow, it's not completely coextensive
with the first נזירות, neziros, right? It adds an extra day, right?
Because it'll end one day later than the first
נזירות. neziros. חלה נזירות על נזירות, Chala neziros al neziros, it takes
effect. Now there's two ways of understanding this. One way, which I
don't know, which is just the what I guess to me seemed
the most obvious way was it just makes it not the exact
same thing, it makes it distinct. If it's the same thing twice,
you know, then it doesn't have any distinct identity. You don't see
it as something else that's hovering. You see it as just you
tried to do the same thing multiple times, you tried to make
yourself the same type of a נזירות neziros multiple times, as opposed
to no, you try to make yourself a distinct thing and therefore
it's distinct and hovering. The ר"ן Ran says a different idea. The
ר"ן Ran actually says no, it's not because it's distinct and hovering.
The ר"ן Ran says what actually it is is that since it
actually the first twenty-nine days nothing took effect, or the first but
day thirty of the second, thirty-one of the first, right, there was
no overlap. That one day, right, took effect because that one day
there was nothing, there was nothing sort of obstructing it. Since that
one day took effect, we have a principle of אין נזירות פחות
משלושים יום. Ein neziros pachot mishloshim yom. You can't have a one
day נזירות. neziros. So since it took effect for one day, everything
then for that day thirty-one you were a נזיר, nazir, and for
that would a נזיר nazir for day thirty-one you're a נזיר nazir
for thirty, for thirty days, you know, from that point on. So
that's the way the ר"ן Ran understands it. Not just conceptually it's
distinct, you tried to make yourself a different type of a נזיר
nazir and therefore it's hovering, but that in fact because it's shifted,
it takes effect, one day does take effect and then everything gets
dragged with that. Yeah.
That thirty-first day has what status?
Your second נזירות. neziros.
Day one of your second נזירות. neziros. Actually, it should be the
last day of your second נזירות, neziros, but since it's the first
observed day of your second נזירות, neziros, then it's going to bring
with it everything else. Okay, because then you אין נזירות פחות משלושים
יום. ein neziros pachot mishloshim yom. All right. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אמר. Amar.
Okay. I guess it should be an interesting נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
Let's say somebody was a, well was a נזיר nazir today and
then he waited a week, and a week later after he was
a week into his נזירות, neziros, he said,
no, wait, how how would this work?
No, that won't work because then it's going to have the same
point as the ר"ן, Ran, it's going to end a day earlier.
Ah, no, no, no. Here.
I right now take a נזירות neziros to last sixty days. I
say I accept upon myself to be a נזיר nazir for sixty
days. Okay. And then
a week in, two weeks in, I say, and now I accept
upon myself a נזירות neziros for thirty days. Okay. So in that
scenario I just gave you, they're clearly distinct. נזירות Neziros number one
is a sixty day נזירות neziros and נזירות neziros number two is
a thirty day נזירות, neziros, and I even accepted נזירות neziros number
two later than נזירות neziros number one. So clearly I'm talking they're
distinct conceptually. But according to the ר"ן, Ran, that might never kick
in because there's no day that the second one actually exists by
itself. So I think there's two ways of looking at this גמרא,
Gemara, right? Is this idea that it needs to be shifted, is
this idea just to make them distinct, not like I said the
same thing twice, I just repeated myself? Right, that's part of the
question. הריני נזיר הריני נזיר. Hareni nazir hareni nazir. What do you
mean? You just repeated yourself. You said the same thing twice. And
he say no, no, you didn't say, they're different, it's just enough
to make them distinct. Or the way the ר"ן Ran understands it,
it's not enough to make them distinct, it actually had to be
one day that the second one can take effect all by itself.
Okay, so that's the position of רב הונא. Rav Huna. Okay. ושמואל
אמר, VeShmuel amar,
now שמואל Shmuel says, אפילו אמר הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר היום.
afilu amar hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir hayom. No, even if the
guy said I'm a נזיר nazir today, I'm a נזיר nazir today,
חלה נזירות עליה. chala neziros aleha.
The second נזירות neziros takes effect. Again, not like you're a double
נזיר nazir now, but the second one is hovering and waiting to
kick in. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולרב הונא, UleRav Huna, according
to רב הונא, Rav Huna, עד דתני. ad detani.
Why not make a distinction between two types of נדרים *nedarim*? I
mean הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר למחר harei ni nazir hayom harei
ni nazir lemachar. *hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir lamachar*. If you were
to say I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* today I'm a נזיר nazir,
*nazir* tomorrow, יש נדר neder בתוך נדר neder *yesh neder betoch neder*.
That's where there would be one נדר neder. *neder* on top of
another. הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר היום harei ni nazir hayom harei
ni nazir hayom, *hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir hayom*, but if you
said I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* today I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir*
today, then אין נדר neder. בתוך נדר *ein neder betoch neder*. It
doesn't take effect. So according to him that not all types of
נזירות nezirus, *neziruses* one can be piled up, only when you shift
them, so why did the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* just blanketly say יש
נדר בתוך נדר *yesh neder betoch neder*? Now of course as the
ראשונים *Rishonim* point out, first of all it's not a blanket statement
because as I told you at the beginning, normal נדר *neder* wouldn't
take effect. If I said קונם כיכר זה עלי קונם כיכר זה
עלי *konam kikar zeh alai konam kikar zeh alai* it would be
meaningless, אין איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur, *ein issur
chal al issur*. But even within the context that we're talking about
נזירות nezirus, *nezirus* and that's our example that נזירות nezirus *nezirus* is
distinct, why didn't you tell us that not all נזירות nezirus. *neziruses*
are the same, that some נזירות nezirus *nezirus* will you know can
be doubled up and some cannot? So according to רב הונא Rav
Huna. *Rav Huna* the fact that it did not make that distinction
just seems to say if you said I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir*
I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* it works, seems to say that even
if they are ממש *mamish* the same statement it can still be
doubled up. Yes.
Based on what we were saying before I'm surprised the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* doesn't ask a better question. You're telling me אין נדר *ein
neder* what does it say יש נדר בתוך נדר *yesh neder betoch
neder* and then you're giving me an example of the only case
that it applies is נזירות nezirus?
*nezirus*. Yeah I know so that is strange that is strange and
it doesn't ask that you're right and it's you know immediately translates
נדר *neder* into נזיר nazir, *nazir* because it's basically making the point
that a normal נדר *neder* cannot be doubled up which is true
you know but okay that you're right that it's not asking but
that's not relevant to this debate about how the double נזירות nezirus,
*nezirus* works. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay קשיא *kasha* you're
right according to רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna* it could have
given an example where double נזירות neziruses. *nezirus* did not work if
they were not at if they were not shifted from one another.
תנן *Tnan*, now let's try to prove you know who's right in
this debate. יש נדר בתוך נדר ואין שבועה shvua בתוך שבועה shvua
*yesh neder betoch neder ve-ein shvua betoch shvua*. היכי דמי Heichi dami,
*Heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא דאמר הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר
למחר Ileima de'amar harei ni nazir hayom harei ni nazir lemachar, *ileima
de-amar hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir lamachar*, if we read like רב
הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna* that by the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* when
the second נזירות nezirus, *nezirus* can take effect is if you said
I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* today I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* tomorrow,
okay so then we have to think about a parallel case by
a שבועה shvua *shvua* because we're saying what works by נזירות nezirus,
*nezirus* does not work by a שבועה shvua *shvua*. דכוותה גבי שבועה
shvua *de-chavaseh gabei shvua* similarly by a שבועה shvua *shvua*.
If a person said שלא אוכל תאנים וחזר ואמר שלא אוכל ענבים
*she-lo ochal te-enim ve-chazar ve-amar she-lo
ochal anavim*, first he says I won't eat figs then he says
I won't eat grapes, אמאי לא חלה שבועה shvua על שבועה shvua
*amai lo chala shvua al shvua*? Why shouldn't it take effect? They're
not related. Now of course you and I will say what? Figs
and grapes? That's apples and oranges. I'm sorry I couldn't resist.
Okay so anyway but it is an apples and oranges type of
a comparison to the other example right one is they overlap for
nine you know for 29 out of 30 days you know it's
not and the one is trying to take effect on top of
the other and actually being blocked right whereas the figs and the
grapes the fig שבועה shvua? *shvua* is over here and the grape
שבועה shvua *shvua* is over here what does that have to do
with anything? Okay so the רן Ran, *Ran* says yes that's true
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now this is why the רן Ran
*Ran* goes his approach is focusing on day 31. When I say
I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* tomorrow if you forget the first 29
days you look at day 30 or day 31 or whatever you
know the non overlap day and there there's no conflict. So if
that works because on that last day there's no conflict well two
שבועות shvuous: *shvuas* that there's no conflict will also work. Okay obviously
there's a bit of a difference so let's see where the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* goes with this. Okay so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says
אמאי לא חלה שבועה shvua על שבועה shvua *amai lo chala shvua
al shvua*? אלא היכי דמי דלא חלה שבועה shvua על שבועה shvua
*ella heichi dami de-lo chala shvua al shvua*? What's the case that
a שבועה shvua *shvua* doesn't take effect on top of another one?
כגון דאמר שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים shvua shelo ochal te'einim, וחזר ואמר
שבועה shvua שלא אוכל תאנים *kegon de-amar shvua she-lo ochal te-enim ve-chazar
ve-amar shvua she-lo ochal te-enim*. You the most obvious case is you
immediately repeated what you said. Okay so if that's not what works
by שבועה shvua *shvua* it is what works by a נזיר nazir
*nazir*. דכוותה גבי נזירות nezirus, *de-chavaseh gabei nezirus* similarly by a נזיר
*nazir* therefore in parallel היכי דמי *heichi dami*? What's the case? דאמר
הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר היום harei ni nazir hayom harei ni
nazir hayom, *de-amar hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir hayom* you try to
do the exact same thing twice. ותני יש נדר בתוך נדר *ve-tani
yesh neder betoch neder* and it does work. קשיא לרב הונא *kasha
le-Rav Huna* that's a challenge on רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*.
Okay so where do you get a case by רב הונא Rav
Huna *Rav Huna* that it's sort of like not a complete overlap
by your שבועה shvua *shvua* and it doesn't work? If it's not
an overlap by the שבועה shvua *shvua* then it should work by
a שבועה shvua *shvua*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says אמר לך
רב הונא Rav Huna *amar lach Rav Huna*, רב הונא Rav Huna.
*Rav Huna* will say to you מתניתין דאמר הריני נזיר היום הריני
נזיר למחר harei ni nazir hayom harei ni nazir lemachar, *masnisin de-amar
hareni nazir hayom hareni nazir lamachar*. No like I said when does
it work by a נזירות nezirus? *nezirus* if there's some shift some
non-overlap. I'm a נזיר *nazir* today and then you say and I'll
be a נזיר *nazir* beginning tomorrow. דכוותה גבי שבועה shvua *de-chavaseh gabei
shvua* similarly by a שבועה shvua. *shvua* דאמר שלא אוכל תאנים וחזר
ואמר שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים וענבים vechazar ve'amar shvua shelo ochal te'einim
ve'anavim, *de-amar she-lo ochal te-enim ve-chazar ve-amar shvua she-lo ochal te-enim ve-anavim*.
Okay so you say a שבועה shvua *shvua* I won't eat figs
and then you say a שבועה shvua *shvua* I won't eat figs
and grapes. Now there's a how do you understand that second שבועה
shvua *shvua*? It could be understood a שבועה shvua *shvua* I won't
eat figs and a and a and a שבועה shvua *shvua* I
won't eat grapes. If so then there's the grape part again there's
no overlap right because the grape part remains totally independent of the
But the way the רן, Ran and this is a very, very
long תוספות Tosfos here, anyway wind up understanding it, but particularly the
רן, Ran it's that you said a שבועה shvua I won't eat
figs and then you said and a שבועה shvua I won't eat
figs and grapes together. Okay, not that I won't eat, yeah, like
whatever in the same meal or you know in the same in
the same morsel, I won't put both of them in my mouth
and eat them at the same time. Okay, now if you say
that, what do you think? Did the second שבועה shvua kick in
or not? So do you say, if you're already prohibited against eating
figs, you cannot add on it a prohibition of eating figs and
grapes together, because you already can't eat figs and grapes together because
you already can't eat figs. That's one way of saying it. But
the other way of saying it is this is conceptually a different
thing. It's true, if you eat figs and grapes together, you'll have
transgressed two שבועות: eating figs and eating figs and grapes. But it's
conceptually a different thing, and even though part of it you're already
foresworn against, but it can, maybe it should take effect. So he's
saying maybe that's exactly the point. By a נזירות, nezirus when there's
an area that they don't overlap, it takes effect, that day 31.
Okay, whereas by figs and grapes, maybe there is an aspect that's
distinct: it's the figs and grapes together, and it's not a complete
coincidence,
coinciding of the two, and nevertheless, it doesn't take effect because if
you already can't eat figs, then it's not meaningful to forbid you
against figs and grapes together because you already can't eat figs. So
let's take a look. It says,
okay, נסיב לה אמר הריני נזיר יום אחד דכוותיה גבי שבועה דאמר
שלא אוכל תאנים וחזר ואמר שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים וענבים דלא חלה.
nasiv lah amar hareini nazir yom echad dechvasia gabei shvua de'amar shelo
ochal te'einim vechazar ve'amar shvua shelo ochal te'einim ve'anavim delo chala. It
wouldn't take effect because the figs are already off limits. So the
גמרא Gemara says is that really true that it doesn't take effect?
והאמר רבא, veha'amar Rava, doesn't רבא Rava say: שבועה shvua שלא אוכל
תאנים,
if somebody says a שבועה shvua I won't eat figs, וחזר ואמר
שבועה shvua שלא אוכל תאנים וענבים, and then he says figs and
grapes, ואכל תאנים. ve'achal te'einim.
Now he ate figs, so he's already transgressed שבועה shevuah, number one.
והפריש קרבן, vehafrish korban, and he separated out a קרבן korban to
bring for trans-violating שבועה shevuah, number one. וחזר ואכל ענבים, vechazar ve'achal
anavim, and then he ate grapes, הוי ליה ענבים חצי שיעור, havei
lei anavim chatzi shiur, regarding שבועה shevuah. number two, the grapes is
only half a transgression, ואין מביאין קרבן על חצי שיעור, ve'ein mevi'in
korban al chatzi shiur, and you can't bring it. Now, okay, so
what's the point? The point is that once you separate off a
קרבן, korban, it segregates out that eating of the of the figs.
Okay? Right? It means that that eating of the figs was a
distinct act, and now I'm eating grapes, it's a new thing. So
I'm only looking at it, well you ate grapes, you haven't yet
violated שבועה shevuah, number two. But implicitly, if I didn't separate out
a קרבן, korban, and I ate the figs, and then I didn't
separate a קרבן, korban, and then I ate the grapes, what's רבא
Rava implicitly telling me? That I would have violated which שבועה? shevuah
שבועה shevuah number two. Right? I mean also שבועה shevuah number one
maybe, but also שבועה shevuah, number two. Is that clear? The fact
that he says that eating grapes alone you don't violate because you've
only done half of it, means that שבועה shevuah. number two is
still binding and you can still violate שבועה shevuah number two. And
if you would have followed the grapes with eating figs, you would
have also violated שבועה shevuah. number two.
Yes, so he ate figs, he violated שבועה shevuah number one, he
brought a קרבן. korban. Then instead of just eating grapes, what if
he just ate figs? He could possibly have been able to eat
just figs, that's also חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur.
No, well שבועה shevuah, number one doesn't go away, so he would
violate שבועה shevuah number one again. Now the question is, right, the
question is how could you ever get to violating שבועה shevuah, number
two without first having violated שבועה shevuah number one? So that's not
spelled out. So the רן Ran says, well,
let's imagine that you forgot about שבועה shevuah number one and somebody
said to you, don't eat those figs and grapes or don't eat
those figs because you'll have done half- you- you took an oath,
I heard you take the oath about figs and grapes. Okay, both
of us forgot a week ago you took an oath just about
figs. And I say to you, don't eat those figs because if
you eat those figs and then you eat the grapes, you'll violate
your שבועה. shevuah And you say I don't care, and you eat
the figs. And then you're about to eat the grapes, don't do
that now you're really- I don't care and you go ahead and
eat it. So in that case, you're only a מזיד meizid on
שבועה shevuah number two, you totally forgot about שבועה shevuah number one,
right? So in that type of a case, you would get lashes
on שבועה shevuah. number two. It's possible to- to- to- I mean,
you would always violate שבועה shevuah number one when you violate שבועה
shevuah number two, but it could be without the same consequence. You
could have forgotten about שבועה number one, right? And then you would
have gone ahead and still get lashes for שבועה number two. So
what's clear from רבא's Rava statement, the fact that he talks about
חצי שיעור, chatzi shiur, is that שבועה number two did take effect,
right? There is a שבועה number two out there. So how can
you say שבועה is different than נזירות, nezirus if by נזירות nezirus
you say it only works when they're not overlapping, well if a
שבועה isn't overlapping, it also works. Maybe you'll have to figure out
how under what circumstances, but it's there, it takes effect. So let's
see what the answer is. And then the גמרא Gemara says, almost,
אלמא היכא דאמר שבועה
שלא אוכל תאנים וחזר ואמר שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים וענבים מיגו דחלה
שבועה אענבים
alma heicha de'amar shvua shelo ochal te'einim vechazar
ve'amar
shvua shelo ochal te'einim ve'anavim migu dechala shvua a'anavim because it takes
effect. It takes effect on the grapes and that's distinct, and that's
a non-overlap part, חייל נמי אתאנים chayil nami ate'einim it takes effect
on the figs. So if there's a non-overlap by the שבועה, it
does take effect, the second one does take effect. Okay, and therefore
the same should be so it's exactly like Rav Huna's idea of
נזירות. nezirus גמרא Gemara says, you know what, Rav Huna לא סבירא
ליה lo sevira lei כרבא. k'Rava. Fine, Rav Huna doesn't hold like
Rava. So according to Rava, whether נזירות nezirus or שבועה, anytime there's
a non-overlap it takes effect. According to Rav Huna, no, that's only
true about a נזיר, it's not true about a שבועה. By a
שבועה, since you already cannot do—and now you understand a little bit
the conceptual difference, right? If I'm already not able to eat figs,
why it doesn't make any sense that I should obligate myself not
to eat figs and grapes? You're already that's already not going to
happen because of שבועה number one, if you keep שבועה number one.
So it doesn't make sense to add on it. Whereas, if I
say I'm a נזיר, I'm a נזיר, I haven't talked about what
I'm going to do, what I'm not going to do. Again, it's
like trying to impact, to impart a state on something, and I
think that allows us to think more conceptually that the second state
is hovering, it just can't take effect because there's a pre-existing state,
when the first one goes away, the second takes effect. Whereas if
you talk about me and what I am and am not going
to do, then you could say it doesn't—it's not sensible to say
I'm not going to do something that I'm already not able to
do for a different reason. Okay? Yes?
Does that explanation make sense to me? Yes, I'm trying to understand
the other side.
Rava that says it takes effect when they don't overlap, well, because
he says the שבועה is not a meaningless שבועה, I mean it's
not the same שבועה. As long as it's different, right? Look, the
same ideas by איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al issur. although
again this is about states of something. If something is just אסור
assur to certain people, then it becomes אסור, assur, a second state
to make it אסור assur to more people, right, that would be
a case where, where you could say a שבועה חלה על שבועה
shevuah chala al shevuah because the second one has a bigger scope.
Okay? Or it's אסור assur in different ways than the first one
is
אסור. assur. Okay, but—well, I'm not sure, excuse me, איסור חל על
איסור. But it's not the same because here no—there's no weightier prohibition,
there's no larger scope, there's no more objects, it's just, don't—it's just,
you're right, like there's nothing you
can—I understand, I mean what you're saying is Rav Huna, which is
what Rav Huna is saying, which is that there's nothing that's added
by saying your second שבועה because you would never have gotten there,
right, you know, if you were observing the first שבועה. So there's
no real-world consequence, if you keep the first שבועה you'll never get
to the second שבועה, nothing more is impacted by that. So that
is, you know, that's Rav Huna's point. By the שבועה no, by
נזיר yes, because it's like hovering and it's distinct. You want to
know Rava? Rava just says as long as they're not the same
thing, you know, they can both take effect, I mean, yeah.
It seems like it's in a process, because the גמרא Gemara is
usually about process not about הלכה, halacha, it seems that
as you said, they're just never comparing apples to apples, from the
משנה Mishnah right through the גמרא. Gemara In the משנה Mishnah, they're
comparing נדר to שבועה, but they chose the one type of נדר
that stands apart, that has a time limit. Right? And here again
they're talking about
figs and grapes, figs, then figs and grapes, they're talking נזיר, נזיר,
the equivalent would be I'm a נזיר, and then he comes back
and says and I'm not going to drink any wine.
Right, I mean
they just never
quite—Right.
You mean like if you really were trying to get something closer,
you would have talked about a שבועה of a certain time and
then a שבועה of a longer time. Somebody said, right, שבועה I
won't eat, שבועה I won't eat this loaf of bread for thirty
days, and then it said and a שבועה that starting tomorrow I
won't eat this loaf of bread for thirty days starting tomorrow. That
would have actually been directly analogous.
Right, right from the משנה Mishnah on down through the discussion of
the גמרא, they're just not really lining things up.
Right.
Yeah. It's a really good question. I mean, yeah, I don't know
what to say. You're right. You're right. Yeah.
Does he have any opinion that accepts the idea of a concurrent
נזירות?
nezirus
Not that I know of. Right. I mean, you're right, that's the
simple sense of the משנה, and the גמרא here hasn't even explicitly
said otherwise. I mean, but—but that's not—Yeah, because
the third today would be—Right.
Well, we're about to take a look at something that's very close
to that, so let's take a look.
Okay. Because that's the מחלוקת machlokes between Rava and Rav Huna, right?
Rava believes that the משנה will admit of that type of over-
that type of distinction, right, so that you could have
one—Yeah, Rava will say, or the—who has the opinion that argued? I
mean, here we have a was it Rava or
Shmuel? Shmuel there, but now it's tied to a position of Rava
here, which would say that if you said I'm a נזיר, I'm
a נזיר, even if it was completely coincided one in the other,
it would still take effect vis-a-vis once the first one was done,
the second one would take effect. Right. Okay, so let's take a
look. So we have this still Rav Huna that says that they
need to be shifted, they can't completely coincide. Shmuel says they can
completely coincide by נזירות, nezirus and this then leads to the comparison
by שבועה. If you have a שבועה that doesn't completely coincide, will
the second שבועה take effect or not? That is
then a consequence of this debate. So the גמרא says like this.
Rav Huna okay, מיתיבי, Meisvei, we're still going to try to sort
of fight this out. מי שנזר שתי נזירות, Mi shenazar shtei nezirus,
somebody took two נזירות. nezirus מנה את הראשונה, Mana es harishona, he
counted the first one והפריש קרבן, ve'hifrish korban, and he separated out
a korban ונשאל עליה, ve'nishal aleha, and then before he brought the
korban, he went to a חכם chacham and he did התרת נדרים.
hataras nedarim. It's completely, it's very funny, how do you do התרת
נדרים, hataras nedarim, I mean, you're in the middle of נזירות, nezirus
the חכם chacham could say had you realized how difficult it would
have been to be a נזיר, would you have ever accepted it,
right? Once you've already lived through the whole thing and you've separated
out your korban, now you're having, now you're having regrets? Anyway, but
okay, for whatever reason, the חכם chacham finds a way to מתיר
matir your נזירות, neziruses right, after, in hindsight you have regrets, because
maybe I don't know if that's good. Anyway, you know, you realized
how hard it was, you know, yes I lived through it, but
it was so terribly hard. So why are you bothering doing, you
know,
uprooting it now? You're done already. Who knows? But after, what?
What happens to that animal?
Well right, and then the question is, does the animal become like
הקדש טעות hekdesh taus and so on exactly. But now you've, you've
retroactively undermined your entire נזירות, neziruses. okay. So, it's asking on the
second נזירות? neziruses.
No, first one, you'll see. עלתה לו שניה בראשונה. Alsa lo shniya
barishona.
So now, your second נזירות neziruses you have fulfilled during those last
thirty days when you thought you were fulfilling your first. Okay. So,
retroactively, you were not a נזיר for the last thirty days of
נזירות nezirus number one, you did away with that נדר. But, because
נזירות nezirus number two, it's not like you get credit, but you
haven't done, you know, נזירות neziros, number two was waiting to take
effect those entire thirty days. So now when we look backwards at
the last thirty days, we realize, oh, we were mistaken. נזירות neziros,
number one didn't exist, that was, that has now disappeared because of
the התרה. hatara. But, again looking backwards we realize, oh, if נזירות
nezirus. one didn't exist, then what, then נזירות two took effect. So
now we retroactively realize that you've been observing נזירות number two these
last thirty days. And that korban would be a korban for נזירות
number two.
So that could be, that could be his motivation and it wouldn't
be so strange that he's doing it.
Motivation, if I were to do a התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim,
then it would still kick in. Exactly. Maybe. Or because of the
second one?
Oh, oh I see. The reason you want to do, oh, it
was so hard the first one, I never would have accepted two.
So why doesn't he get a heter on number two? I don't
know rather than number one.
Yeah, why does the גמרא have to have it be למפרע? lemafrei'a?
Well, it's a much more interesting case. Maybe it's a bit of
a חידוש? chiddush? Well, that's true, exactly. Anyway, okay.
היכי דמי, what's the case? אילימא דאמר הריני נזיר היום harei ni
nazir hayom הריני harei, נזיר למחר, if it was that case, so
אמאי עלתה לו שניה בראשונה? amai alsa lo shniya barishona? Why did
you fulfill it? It was one day too, you know, one day
insufficient. If
retroactively you've only done the last thirty days, but the second one
kicked in, so you have one day left for the second one,
so it hasn't totally satisfied it. אלא פשיטא דאמר הריני נזיר היום
הריני נזיר
היום. Ela peshita de'amar harei ni nazir hayom harei ni nazir hayom.
If you said הריני נזיר היום harei ni nazir hayom, twice. And
we see that even when you say it twice and they completely
coincide, the second one is still there hovering. So we see like
שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, ותיובתא דרב הונא, ve'tiyufta de'Rav Huna, it's a contradiction
to רב הונא. Rav Huna לא לעולם הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר
למחר. Lo le'olam harei ni nazir hayom harei ni nazir lemachar. No,
it would still be the הריני נזיר היום Hareini Nazir Hayom, הריני
נזיר למחר. ומאי עלתה, U'mai alsa, what does it mean it counted?
לבר מההוא יומא, Le'var me'ahu yoma, it means the last twenty-nine days
counted and you've got one day left, and maybe the korban, who
knows about it, we'll have to worry about
it. Okay. אינמי Inami or כגון שקיבל שתי נזירות בבת אחת. kegon
she'kibel shtei nezirus be'vas achas. There's a case that even רב הונא
Rav Huna would agree. That I say right now, and this is
important because this gets to conceptually what the issue was, I say
right now, I am a, I am two, I'm accepting upon myself
two נזירות starting today. Okay. So you explicitly say in your one
statement I'm accepting two נזירות. So what we see, if רב הונא
Rav Huna agrees there, what we see is that רב הונא Rav
Huna does not have a problem conceptually with saying that the second
one can be totally coinciding and hovering and waiting and so on.
And that's when I say I'm accepting upon myself two נזירות. And
then when the first one goes away, whether it went away retroactively
the whole thirty days or whether it ends because thirty days are
over, then the second one kicks in. You don't need that extra
day at the end. The first one can be completely, second one
completely overlapping and hovering. What is his problem? His problem is how
you say it. If you say הריני נזיר היום, Hareini Nazir Hayom
this gets back to the point I made way at the beginning.
If you say הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר היום, Hareini Nazir Hayom,
Hareini Nazir Hayom, then we'll just say you just said the same
thing twice. You didn't say anything different. Okay, there's nothing about that
second statement that makes us think that it's anything more than repeating
what you said earlier. Alright. So if you said הריני נזיר היום
Hareini Nazir Hayom הריני נזיר למחר, now you've said something different. If
you said הריני,
I'm obligated upon myself two נזירות starting today, fine, that's what you
want to do, you got one takes effect and the other hovers.
But if you say הריני נזיר היום הריני נזיר היום, then you're
just repeating yourself. So then it turns out that רב הונא Rav
Huna is not so different conceptually. Conceptually he totally accepts that you
can have this model of completely overlapping. completely being, not that extra
day that then brings everything with it, completely existing one on top
of the other, but nevertheless, you know, just waiting to take effect
till the first one ends. The only question is, is that what
you actually said? If it's clear that that's what you said, that'll
work. But if you say you repeat yourself, and there's nothing distinct
about the second one, then we say it's not a... that makes
a lot of sense. Why don't I just look, when you say
הריני נזיר היום, that you're just repeating what you said earlier? Right?
I don't know. What would he say if you said הריני נזיר
היום and then you said, I accept upon myself another נזירות starting
today? Okay, a second one, in addition to the first one. Would
that work? I don't know, right? Maybe not. Maybe it's not exact...
just what you said. Maybe again it's this issue of, of do
they take effect in an order? If one took effect this minute
and the next one tried to take effect a minute later, then
we could say that if the second one is no different than
the first, then it's meaningless. Even if you tried, even if you
said הריני נזיר היום and then you waited a minute and said,
and now I accept upon myself a second נזירות in addition to
the first, then maybe he would also say that doesn't work. Even
though you're trying to do a second one, right? If the first
one already exists, that statement is meaningless. It's not doing anything new.
But if you said, I accept two נזירות, because it's happening at
the same time, we can't say part of your statement is meaningless.
Okay, but still, nevertheless, what's important is, is that conceptually he allows
for this model where you have two totally coincidental נזירות, one on
top of the other, and the second one waiting to take effect.
And they can be exactly the same time frame. The question is,
how do you create that reality? Can you create it after one
exists and trying to put one on top of it? That's what
שמואל Shmuel says. רב הונא Rav Huna, says no, if the first
one already exists, the second one can't be put on top unless
it's somehow distinct. The only way you can create that model is
if you actually did both at the same time. So that's an
important חידוש chiddush which I don't think we would have expected, right,
in רב הונא.
Rav Huna That's what you just said.
שמואל Shmuel says if it already exists, then you can't come and
put something on top of it. No, שמואל Shmuel says you can
put something on top of it even if it already exists. רב
הונא Rav Huna says, I... רב הונא says I can create this
model if I did it all at once, but if something was...
the obligation was already there, then the second... the second thing I'm
doing has to do something different than already exists. Even if I'm
trying to do the same thing, I'm not just repeating myself, I
have to actually do something different if the first thing already exists.
Now the last thing I'll say is the idea that the ר"ן
got, which is, you know what? He says, I don't really get
the גמרא's question, because רב הונא really could agree in this case
of התרת נדרים. Hataras Nedarim. Because in the case of התרת נדרים,
Hataras Nedarim, then in hindsight the second statement was actually completely meaningful,
right? At the time we thought your second statement did nothing, had
no effect, because an obligation existed, right? If you said הריני נזיר
היום הריני נזיר היום, רב הונא would say your second statement means
nothing because you've already created a נזירות. Now we go to רב
הונא a week later and say, רב הונא, wait, I gave you
an update. This guy went to a חכם chacham and he did
a התרה hatara on his נדר. Okay? He says, oh, so now
looking back, I see that his second statement actually was meaningful and
it did kick in, because his first... now his first statement meant
nothing in hindsight. So that's what... so the ר"ן says that the
גמרא did not have to say this case of התרה hatara was
a case where he said one day later, מחר. machar. In this
case where retroactively you made the first statement void, then even רב
הונא could agree that in that case the second statement would work,
yeah.
That's just what רב הונא meant in that case according to the
ר"ן is the second statement is not meaningful yet.
Right. And that's exactly right. It's or, or based on the facts
as they are now, the second statement did nothing and therefore is
void. But if in hindsight we have voided the first statement, then
the second statement now in hindsight becomes completely meaningful.
And instituted retroactively.
Exactly. Exactly. So maybe you could say if it wasn't meaningful at
the time, it doesn't retroactively become meaningful. Anyway, we will end with
this very fascinating debate which we have yet to see the end
of.
Great.